A Guide to the University of Virginia Archives Authority File, 1924, 1953-2008
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
University of Virginia Archives Authority File 1924, 1953-2008
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
RG-12/12/1.081
ca. 800 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The collection was an internal archival transfer made on February 20, 2008.
Scope and Content
The collection contains files (ca. 800 items) on reference topics researched for patrons and University offices by the staff of Special Collections.
Among the many topics are administrative committees; affirmative action for employees; African Americans at the University, including a report by Ervin L. Jordan, Jr., and a 1929 master's thesis "The Negro in Charlottesville and Albemarle County," by Marjorie Irwin; art; athletics in 1951 and 1978 (Gooch and Corrigan reports); Beta Bridge; Blandy Farm; a selective U. Va. bibliography; buildings; the cemetery; Center for Advanced Studies in the Sciences; co-education (including the Woody report); cheers, fight songs, colors, legends, mace, motto and traditions; report on education and employment opportunities, obligations and rights (Rotch report); fraternities and societies including Seven Society; origin of various schools; student radicals and student strike; the University Cafeteria on "The Corner"; the White Burkett Miller Center; and World War II.
People include: Mitzi Clark, Betty Cocke, James Mercer Garnett, Alexander Garrett, Gessner Harrison, James Hay, Jr., "Pop" Lannigan, James Rogers McConnell, Dumas Malone, Arthur J. Morris, Georgia O'Keeffe, William Howard Perkinson, Angelika Powell, Harry Rogers Pratt, University of Virginia Presidents Edwin A. Alderman, John Lloyd Newcomb, Colgate Darden and Edgar Shannon, Albert Tuttle, Charles Scott Venable and Woodrow Wilson.
Arrangement
The files are arranged alphabetically by topic.
Contents List
- Academic Processions 1964 September 24, 1 item (Box-folder 1:1)
  Includes press release on Dean Runk's promotion to Grand Marshal of the University.
- Administrative Committees 1957-1982 August, 37 items (Box-folder 1:2)
  Includes memoranda discussing attached member lists.
- Administrative Reorganization 1967 May-1983 October, 3 items (Box-folder 1:3)
  Includes organizational flow chart, Inside UVA clipping, and Herald Hobson and Associates report "Administration of the University of Virginia at the Senior Level."
- Admissions, Office of 1947 April 22, 1 item (Box-folder 1:4)
  Includes memorandum to Dean Ferguson from the President clarifying the position of Dean of Admissions.
- Affirmative Action 1978 December 1, 2 items (Box-folder 1:5)
  Includes University Register article "Affirmative Action: A History" by Robert H. Trent.
- Affirmative Action Plan 1978 June 1, 1 item (Box-folder 1:6)
  Includes report "University of Virginia Affirmative Action Plan for Equal Employment Opportunity."
- African-American 1950-1973, 15 items (Box-folder 1:7)
  Includes Cavalier Daily clippings regarding African-American enrollment and official University statement on African-American student experience.
- African-American 1987 September, 1 item (Box-folder 1:8)
  "Blacks and the University of Virginia: An Overview 1819-1987." Includes report by Ervin L. Jordan, Jr.
- African-American 1929, 1 item (Box-folder 1:9)
  "The Negro in Charlottesville and Albemarle County" by Marjorie Irwin, Master's thesis.
- African Studies n.d., 3 items (Box-folder 1:9a)
  Includes annotated list Non-Federal Archives and Manuscripts Relating to Africa, regarding University manuscript collections, compiled by Aloha South and related guide and corrections.
- Albemarle County n.d., 1 item (Box-folder 1:9b)
  Includes "Selective Bibliography For Use in Compiling Information for a Pageant in Honor of the 200th Anniversary of Charlottesville, Virginia."
- Alderman, Edwin Anderson [1924-1938], 5 items (Box-folder 1:10)
  Includes CV, "Edwin Anderson Alderman: Commoner of Southern Education" by D. Ramsey, "The Alderman Library at the University of Virginia" from The Alumni News.
- Alumni Association 1980 February 4, 3 items (Box-folder 1:11)
  Includes articles from Cavalier Daily (duplicates).
- Alumni Patents Foundation n.d., 1 item (Box-folder 1:12)
  Includes article about new president of Patents board.
- Appointments 1969 December-1989 August, 17 items (Box-folder 1:13)
  Includes news clippings about appointments of deans, department heads, and provosts.
- Archives 1977 April 1, 1 item (Box-folder 1:14)
  Includes University Register article "Documenting the University's roots...the University Archives."
- Art: Index Printout 1988 August 29, 1 item (Box-folder 1:15)
  Includes list of all artwork on display in University buildings.
- Art: Portraits at University of Virginia 1981 February 10, 1 item (Box-folder 1:16)
  Includes list of all portraits owned by University.
- Asian Studies n.d., 1 item (Box-folder 1:16a)
  Includes list of Asian-related materials in University manuscript collection.
- Beta Bridge 1981 March-1986 September, 2 items (Box-folder 1:17)
  Includes Cavalier Daily articles about the history of Beta Bridge.
- "Bibliography of Articles concerning University of Virginia prepared by Robert L. Baxter" n.d., 1 item (Box-folder 1:18)
- Bishko, Charles n.d., 2 items (Box-folder 1:19)
  Includes retirement ceremony program and guest list.
- Blandy Farm 1936-1977, 5 items (Box-folder 1:20)
  Includes the will of Graham Blandy, information about the experimental farm and its researchers, correspondence regarding renting of the farm.
- Blough, Carman G. 1970 March, 1 item (Box-folder 1:21)
  Includes Florida Institute of Certified Public Accountants (FICPA) article about Blough, Chair of Accounting of McIntire School of Commerce.
- Blue Ridge Sanatorium 1978 July 15, 1 item (Box-folder 1:22)
  Includes University Register article "Blue Ridge joins University Hospital."
- Buildings: Anatomical Hall 1936 -1975, 12 items (Box-folder 1:23)
  Includes correspondence regarding its history.
- Buildings: "Brief Biographical Sketches of the Professors for whom the Dormitories at the University of Virginia Were Named." 1978, 3 items (Box-folder 1:24)
- Buildings: "Buildings, Statues, Etc., References" 1950, 1 item (Box-folder 1:25)
  Includes report compiled by Alderman Library of factual information on University buildings and statues.
- Buildings: Cabell Hall, Old and New: History of [1970], 3 items (Box-folder 1:26)
- Buildings: Carr's Hill 1962 July 14, 1 item (Box-folder 1:27)
  Includes correspondence about Field House.
- Buildings: Chapel 1950-1998, 18 items (Box-folder 1:28)
  Includes news clippings regarding the chapel and library request for information about the chapel's history.
- Buildings: Chemistry Building n.d., 1 item (Box-folder 1:29)
  Includes information about building's history.
- Buildings: Fayerweather Hall n.d., 1 item (Box-folder 1:30)
  Includes news clipping about the building's history.
- Building: Naming of... 1959-2008, 4 items (Box-folder 2:1)
  Naming of...: Includes correspondence regarding naming of Scott Stadium, Cavalier Daily news clipping, and draft of report "Naming of University Buildings for Persons" by Francis King, Jr.
- Buildings: Pavilions 1965-1988, 13 items (Box-folder 2:2)
  Includes Cavalier Daily news clippings and lists of past pavilion occupants.
- Buildings: Rotunda 1937-1988, 10 items (Box-folder 2:3)
  Includes articles discussing its history and design, Cavalier Daily news clippings regarding release of Rotunda stamp, and report "The Present Condition and Proposed Future Use of the Rotunda or Library Building at the University of Virginia."
- Buildings: William Faulkner House n.d., 2 items (Box-folder 2:4)
  Includes historical information and brochure.
- Buildings: Wilson Hall 1977 January, 1 item (Box-folder 2:5)
  Includes construction notes.
- Cataloging: "A Ballad of Books, or, a tale told by an idiot, full of sound and fury signifying nothing." [1938-1939], 1 item (Box-folder 2:6)
- Cemetary n.d., 1 item (Box-folder 2:7)
  Includes "Notes on the History of the University Cemetary."
- Cemetary: Civil War 1905, 1 item (Box-folder 2:8)
  Includes "The Honor Roll of the University of Virginia: Names that Cannot Die."
- Cemetary: Soldiers' Cemetary n.d., 1 item (Box-folder 2:9)
  Includes "Keys to the Map of the Soldiers' Cemetary" and rosters of the deceased.
- Cemetary: University [1980]-1983, 4 items (Box-folder 2:10)
  Includes Cavalier Daily news clippings and copy of "Notes on the History of the University Cemetery."
- Center for the Advanced Studies in the Sciences 1966, 1 item (Box-folder 2:11)
  Regarding the Science Development Grant and development of the center.
- Cheers 1981 March, 3 items (Box-folder 2:12)
  Includes Cavalier Daily news clippings about "Wah-Hoo-Wah" cheer.
- Clark, Mitzi 2008 October (Box-folder 2:12a)
  Article in Kiplinger's concerning this former volunteer in Special Collections.
- Clinch Valley College [1974], 1 item (Box-folder 2:13)
  Includes report "Clinch Valley College and its Area" by Edward L. Henson, Jr. (president day University of Virginia at Wise).
- Cocke, Miss Betty: Rooming House 1977, 5 items (Box-folder 2:14)
  Includes report "Student Life at Miss Betty's: The Student Experience at Miss Betty Cocke's Rooming House at the University of Virginia" and related correspondence.
- Co-education: Newspaper clippings 1957-1995, 41 items (Box-folder 2:15)
  Includes Cavalier Daily and Daily Progress articles about history of women at the University of Virginia and co-education.
- Co-education: Woody Report 1968 November, 1 item (Box-folder 2:16)
  "Report on the Admission of Women to the College of Arts and Sciences."
- Colors 31 May 1962, 2 items (Box-folder 2:17)
  Includes correspondence regarding history of the school colors.
- Committees 1977-1978 October, 2 items (Box-folder 2:18)
  Includes lists of administration committees in the University Register.
- Committees 1977 April 28, 2 items (Box-folder 2:19)
  Counselors Committee: Cavalier Daily article "Counselors Committee: helping students understand sexuality."
- Consultative: Research Center 1976-1977, 10 items (Box-folder 2:20)
  Includes newsletters, a publication of the University's general educational assistance center.
- Copeley 1921 February 21, 1 item (Box-folder 2:21)
  Includes correspondence regarding Massie's gift of a parcel of land to the University.
- Corner Cafeteria (Box-folder 2:22)
- Corrigan Report 1978, 2 items (Box-folder 2:23)
  Regarding the state of college athletics and University athletics.
- Deans [1905-1957], 2 items (Box-folder 3:1)
  Includes list of past deans and report "Installation of the first president of the University of Virginia: Alderman."
- Degrees 1819-1919, 2 items (Box-folder 3:2)
  Includes "History of the University of Virginia 1819-1919" and "A Sketch of the University."
- Development, Office of 1969 April 7, 1 item (Box-folder 3:3)
  Includes draft of report by William A. Hobbes regarding history of development of University.
- Development, Vice President for 1976-1980, 2 items (Box-folder 3:4)
  Cavalier Daily and University Register news clippings regarding John J. Owen's appointment and retirement.
- Easters 1976-1982, 7 items (Box-folder 3:5)
  Includes The University Journal and Cavalier Daily news clippings regarding the history of and cancellation of Easters week celebration.
- Endowed Professorships 1983-1984, 3 items (Box-folder 3:6)
  Includes list of endowed professorship positions.
- Engineering and Applied Sciences 1977 December 1, 1 item (Box-folder 3:7)
  Includes article on departmental reorganization from the University Register.
- Engineering and Applied Sciences: Humanities Division 1983 November, 1 item (Box-folder 3:8)
  Includes report "A Brief Account of the Origin of the Humanities Division from 1932-1966" by Joseph L. Vaughan.
- Engineering and Applied Sciences: Newspaper Clippings 1936-1960, 39 items (Box-folder 3:9)
  Regarding Thornton Hall and Defense Training Courses during World War II.
- English Department n.d., 1 item (Box-folder 3:10)
  Includes description of course tracks available by Professor Charles Kent.
- Equal Opportunity Program Office 1977-1979, 4 items (Box-folder 3:11)
  Includes news clippings of The Declaration and Inside UVA the administration of the EOP office.
- Faculty 1960 February 1, 1 item (Box-folder 3:12)
  Includes memorandum regarding tenure and academic freedom of faculty at University of Virginia.
- Fight Songs 1981 March 4, 2 items (Box-folder 3:13)
  Includes Cavalier Daily articles (duplicate of "Cheers").
- Fraternities 1976-1987, 9 items (Box-folder 3:14)
  Includes Cavalier Daily news clippings of the history, maps of houses and "Fraternities and Societies at Virginia" informational booklet.
- Garnett, James Mercer n.d., 1 item (Box-folder 3:15)
  Includes biographical sketch.
- Garrett, Alexander [196?], 1 item (Box-folder 3:16)
- Gooch Report 1951, 2 items (Box-folder 3:17)
  "Report of the Athletic Committee of the Academic Faculty of the University of Virginia."
- Harrison, Gessner 1978 April-June, 5 items (Box-folder 3:18)
  Includes correspondence with James Madison University regarding biographical research of Harrison.
- Hay, James n.d., 1 item (Box-folder 3:19)
  Includes "An Honor Man," a biographical booklet prepared by the Purple Shadows society.
- Health Sciences Library 1972-1979, 3 items (Box-folder 3:20)
  Includes medical library's history, building proposals, and Daily Progress article regarding death of library director, Dr. W. Moll.
- Honor Committee 1976-1985, 5 items (Box-folder 3:21)
  Includes Honor System research, commission, and Cavalier Daily news clippings.
- Jefferson Society 1958-1961, 11 items (Box-folder 3:22)
  Includes Cavalier Daily news clippings regarding the history of literary societies at University of Virginia and current events of the Jefferson Society.
- Jefferson, Thomas 1970-1978, 6 items (Box-folder 3:23)
  Includes news clippings regarding Jefferson's architecture and research correspondence regarding Jefferson's debt to C. Peyton.
- Lannigan, "Pop" 1901-1938, 28 items (Box-folder 3:24)
  Includes BOV minutes, news clippings, Corks and Curls, University of Virginia Alumni Bulletin, and University of Virginia Alumni News: complied research materials.
- Law School 1979 January 15, 1 item (Box-folder 3:25)
  Includes The University Register article "Phase II of Law School Opens."
- Laws and Enactments 1819-?, 3 items (Box-folder 3:26)
  Includes "The Statute Establishing the University of Virginia", "Notes Concerning University of Virginia Laws and Enactments" compiled by W. R. Haynes, and "Proposed Modification of Plan of Government for University of Virginia."
- Lawn 1980-1991, 3 items (Box-folder 3:27)
  Includes Cavalier Daily news clippings regarding residents, endowmed rooms, and legends.
- Logos [1980], 2 items (Box-folder 3:28)
  Includes logos used by the University.
- McConnell, Jason Rogers: Statue 1982, 3 items (Box-folder 3:29)
  News clippings.
- McCormic Observatory 1964, 2 items (Box-folder 3:30)
  News clippings from the Washington Post and the Alumni News.
- McGregor Room n.d., 1 item (Box-folder 3:31)
  Includes announcement of dedication of McGregor Room in Alderman Library in Alumni News.
- Mace n.d., 2 items (Box-folder 3:32)
  Includes information about the silver mace used in University processions from Pictorial History of the University of Virginia by William B. O'Neal and Mr. Jefferson's University by Virginius Dabney.
- Malone, Dumas 1979-1987, 8 items (Box-folder 3:33)
  Includes biographical sketch and news clippings of Dumas' work as Jefferson biographer.
- Medical Alumni Association 1977, 1 item (Box-folder 3:34)
  Includes report "The Origin and Early Days of the Medical Alumni Association of the University of Virginia" by Dr. Beverly Smith.
- Miscellaneous Newspaper Clippings 1976 August 30, 17 items (Box-folder 3:35)
  "Administration Facebook": Includes clippings from The Declaration.
- Miscellanous Newspaper Clippings n.d., 9 items (Box-folder 3:36)
  "Charlottesville Personalities": Includes biographical sketches of University officials and professors.
- Miscellaneous Newspaper Clippings 1977-1981, 6 items (Box-folder 3:37)
  Obituaries.
- Miscellaneous Newspaper Clippings [1960-1982], 66 items (Box-folder 4:1)
  Includes Cavalier Daily articles regarding student life, administration, and University events.
- Morea n.d., 1 item (Box-folder 4:2)
  Includes article "Historic Property Threatened by Plan for Student Housing."
- Morris, Arthur J. n.d., 1 item (Box-folder 4:3)
- Motto 1986 December 16, 1 item (Box-folder 4:4)
  Includes memorandum regarding records of an official motto for University of Virginia.
- Names 1969 July, 1 item (Box-folder 4:5)
  "An Index to Personal Names Commemorated at the University of Virginia."
- Observatory Hill n.d., 1 item (Box-folder 4:6)
  Includes an article about the Observatory.
- O'Keefe, Georgia [1915-2001], 2 items (Box-folder 4:7)
  Includes compiled biography, records of class registration, and course instruction at University of Virginia.
- Perkinson, William Howard n.d., 1 item (Box-folder 4:8)
  Includes biographical sketch and enrollment records at University of Virginia.
- Ph.D Institute 1979-1980, 3 items (Box-folder 4:9)
  Includes information booklet "Career Opportunities: A Summer Institute for Ph.D.'s in the Humanities and Social Sciences", summer program proposal, and news clipping announcing the program.
- Poe's Room 1974-1992, 2 items (Box-folder 4:10)
  Includes Cavalier Daily article "Poe's Room Refurbished" and correspondence regarding research on vandalism to the room.
- Powell, Angelika 1981 April 8, 1 item (Box-folder 4:11)
  Includes Cavalier Daily article "Endurance" about Powell's, a University librarian, life in East Germany during and after WWII.
- Pratt, Harry Rogers n.d., 2 items (Box-folder 4:12)
  Includes news clippings and Charlottesville Personalities biographical sketch.
- President of the University [1976], 2 items (Box-folder 4:13)
  Includes biographical sketches of Alderman, Newcomb, Darden, Shannon, and Hereford.
- President of the University: Darden 1947-1958, 54 items (Box-folder 4:14)
  Includes news clippings about President Darden, Inaugural Address of President Newcomb.
- President of the University-Newcomb 1933-1934, 7 items (Box-folder 4:15)
  Includes news clippings about President Newcomb from The Evening Leader, The Richmond Times-Dispatch, and The Daily Progress.
- President of the University: Shannon, Edgar Finley 1957-1974, 74 items (Box-folder 4:16)
  Includes news clippings about President Shannon and Mrs. Shannon, Inaugural Address of President Shannon.
- Rector and the Board of Visitors 1973 April, 2 items (Box-folder 4:17)
  Includes list of BOV members from 1819-1973.
- Religious Studies, Department: History of [1895-1967], 4 items (Box-folder 4:18)
  Includes newspaper clippings and report including naming of John Cary Religion Department.
- Research and Information Services n.d., 5 items (Box-folder 5:1)
  Includes list of Local History and University of Virginia subject headings used by the reference department, and a copy of "Buildings, Statues, Etc. of the University of Virginia."
- "Rotch Report" 1969 August-September, 2 items (Box-folder 5:2)
  Report of the President's Committee on Education and Employment Opportunities, Obligations, and Rights: Includes report and memorandum regarding the report.
- Rotunda Bell 1827 November, 2 items (Box-folder 5:3)
  Includes correspondence regarding the casting and shipping of the bell.
- Russian Studies 1981, 2 items (Box-folder 5:3a)
  Includes excerpt from The Russian Empire and Soviet Union: A Guide to Manuscripts and Archival Materials in the United States with the materials from Virginia and draft of listed manuscripts from Alderman library.
- Schools of the University: Origins [1976], 11 items (Box-folder 5:4)
  Includes "Notes on the Beginnings of the Schools of the University of Virginia", final report and draft of "Origins of the Schools of the University of Virginia", and correspondence regarding the research.
- Scholarship Funds 1962, 2 items (Box-folder 5:5)
  Includes detailed report on scholarships dedicated to and funded by donors and correspondence regarding the report.
- Seal [1956], 3 items (Box-folder 5:6)
  Includes Gaines' notes on the University of Virginia seal, correspondence regarding research of the seal, and copies of past University seals.
- Societies: Mystical Seven (Hands and Torch/Beta Theta Pi, Eli Banana) 1889-1961, 2 items (Box-folder 5:7)
  Includes "History of the Hands and Torch Chapter of the Mystic Seven Fraternity" and Cavalier Daily article "Eli Banana" regarding the history of the society.
- Societies: Sevens 1955-1996, 3 items (Box-folder 5:8)
  Includes news clippings from The Daily Progress, The C-Ville, The Cavalier Daily regarding the history and activities of the Seven Society and "The Fantastic 7 Society."
- Speakers 1900-1999, 9 items (Box-folder 5:9)
  Includes list of speakers for Convocation, Founder's Day, and Graduation/Final Exercises.
- Sports, University: Newcomb's Term 1934-1935, 60 items (Box-folder 5:10)
  Includes news clippings from the Washington Times, the Richmond Times-Dispatch, Charlotte Observer, Roanoke Times, and other national newspapers.
- St. Louis World's Fair (The Louisiana Purchase Expedition) [1904], 2 items (Box-folder 5:11)
- Student Health 1984 August 2, 1 item (Box-folder 5:12)
  Includes Cavalier Daily feature "An Ailing Student Health Center."
- Student Legal Services (SLS) 1978 February 2, 1 item (Box-folder 5:13)
  Includes The Declaration article "SLS: Struggle for the Legal Tender."
- Student Life 1934-1935, 1 item (Box-folder 5:14)
  Includes report "A Radical Tradition: Student Life at the University of Virginia, 1934-1935" by Richard Boskey on May 7, 1978.
- Student Officers 1979-1989, 9 items (Box-folder 5:15)
  Includes rosters of student leaders of University organizations.
- Student Profile 1977-1979, 3 items (Box-folder 5:16)
  Includes reports "The University of Virginia First-Year Student Profile" complied by the Office of the Dean of Students.
- Student Strike 1970 May 5-12, 1 item (Box-folder 5:17)
  Includes detailed notes on May Day strike.
- Sundials 1930-1990, 4 items (Box-folder 5:18)
  Includes Daily Progress article "Sundials Watching Time Go By", correspondence regarding inscriptions on the sundials at the University of Virginia, and sketches of the sundials at the University.
- Thomas Jefferson Award 1951-1987, 6 items (Box-folder 5:19)
  Includes correspondence regarding the establishment and the history of the honor and a list of award recipients.
- Tuttle, Albert Henry n.d., 1 item (Box-folder 5:20)
  Includes biographical sketch of Professor of Biology, Tuttle.
- University Press of Virginia 1962-1963, 3 items (Box-folder 5:21)
  Includes booklet by Victor Reynolds, and correspondence and "Notes on the Establishment of the University Press of Virginia" both by President Shannon.
- University of Virginia: General 1981 August, 1 item (Box-folder 5:22)
  Includes issue of Travel and Leisure regarding college towns, including Charlottesville by Jean Lawrence.
- Venable, Charles Scott n.d., 1 item (Box-folder 5:23)
  Includes biographical sketch by William M. Thornton.
- Vice Presidents for Administration 1982 July 1, 1 item (Box-folder 5:24)
  Includes Inside UVA article "University Prepares for Fund Cutbacks."
- Virginia Convention of 1829 1939 November 13, 1 item (Box-folder 5:24a)
  Includes list of University manuscripts, Cabell, Stanard, and Ambler papers, pertaining to the convention.